A Guide to the James P. King Collection, 1922-1926
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
James P. King Collection, 1922-1926
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1970-005
0.5 cu. ft. 1 box
College memorabilia of James Peter King, a 1926 graduate of Virginia Tech.
King, James P.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The James P. King Collection was donated to Special Collections in 1970 and 1971.
Biographical Note
James Peter King, the son of Dr. John C. and Fannie Price King, was born in Virginia on December 12, 1902. In the early 20th century, the younger King moved with his family from Marion, Virginia to Radford, where his father established St. Albans Psychiatric Hospital. As a student at Virginia Tech, James "Jimmy" King was a member of the Cotillion Club and worked as circulation manager and associate manager of the school newspaper, then known as the Virginia Tech. He also served as a football manager, class secretary, and on the Ring Committee. In his senior year, King served as business manager of the 1926 Bugle. After graduating from Virginia Tech in 1926 and the University of Virginia Medical School in 1930, King returned to Radford and worked at St. Albans, eventually becoming the hospital's medical director. He retired in 1976. Dr. King was twice married (to Rose Mary Rasmussen and Anna Taylor Whitman) and was the father of four children. He died on January 18, 2004.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains college memorabilia collected by James P. King, a 1926 graduate of Virginia Tech. The collection includes such memorabilia as programs, tickets, and associated ephemera from college events; a scrapbook; photographs and artwork used in the 1926 Bugle; and a folder of personal memorabilia from King's college years.
Among the programs in the collection are several for sporting events, including several football games against the Virginia Military Institute. Also included is a program from a 1922 minstrel show. Other ephemeral items include Cotillion Club dance cards, menus for banquets sponsored by the Cotillion Club and others; tickets to sports games, dances, and other events; invitations; sports team schedules; a YMCA membership card; an alcoholic abstinence pledge card; and a pair of advertisements for Glen-Minnich Clothing, of Roanoke, Virginia.
A folder of class records in the collection contains various rosters of the class of 1926 and minutes from class meetings. Also included in the collection are several illustrations from the V.P.I. Psalm Book; several newspaper clippings about Virginia Tech; and a folder of King's personal college memorabilia, including a notice about a college beauty contest, a Virginia Tech Alumni Association bond, text of a speech delivered by King before the Richmond alumni chapter, various telegrams, themes by King on Bald Knob and the Virginia Tech freshman snowball fight, leave of absence requests, and an account of the 1924 barrack fire.
A scrapbook in the collection contains materials similar to those found elsewhere in the collection: newspaper clippings, photographs (of football players, teams and games), dance cards, and invitations. Also in the collection are a number of loose photographs of various Virginia Tech sports teams and individual athletes, activities of the Virginia Tech Corps of Cadets, and campus scenery.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by item type.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Copies of the V.P.I. Psalm Book may be found in the Rare Book Collection.
Separated Materials
The following items were removed from the collection to be cataloged for the Rare Book Collection:
World War Memorial Hall Fund, [Blacksburg, VA: Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1923].
Students' Hand-book of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute, v. 27 [Blacksburg, VA: Young Men's Christian Association, 1922].
A photograph of the 1925 football team had been removed from the collection and added to the Photograph Collection some time after the collection was accessioned. Because it is an oversized photograph and would have required separate housing anyhow, the photograph has been kept in the Photograph Collection.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute
Local Subjects:
University Archives
Contents List
- Programs (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Minstrel show, 1922
  - Track meet, 1923
  - Commencement, 1924
  - Football games
    - vs. Virginia Military Institute, 1922
    - vs. North Carolina State, 1923
    - vs. University of Maryland, 1924
    - vs. Virginia Military Institute, 1924
    - University of Richmond vs. University of Maryland, 1924
    - vs. Auburn, 1925
    - vs. Hampden-Sidney College, 1925
    - vs. Virginia Military Institute, 1925
    - vs. Virginia, n.d., [2 copies]
- Dance cards, 1924-1926, n.d. (Box-folder 1-2)
- Menus (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Cotillion Club banquet, 1923-1925; [3 items]
  - Monogram Club banquet, 1925
  - Thanksgiving dinner, 1922-1924; [2 items]
- Tickets and passes, 1922-1925, n.d. (Box-folder 1-4)
- Ephemera, 1923-1924, n.d. (Box-folder 1-5)
- Class of 1926 records, 1923-1926 (Box-folder 1-6)
- V.P.I. Psalm Book illustrations, [1924] (Box-folder 1-7)
- Newspaper clippings, 1924, n.d. (Box-folder 1-8)
- Personal memorabilia, 1922-1925, n.d. (Box-folder 1-9)
- Scrapbook, 1922-1924, n.d. (Box-folder 1-10)
- Artwork for 1926 Bugle, [1926] (Box-folder 1-11)
- Contact sheets for 1926 Bugle, [1926] (Box-folder 1-12)
- Photographs, [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Baseball team, 1925
  - Basketball players, 1924
    - Carroll
    - Ebert
    - Cousins
    - King
    - Roberts
    - Rutherford
    - Sutton
  - Football players, ca. 1924-1926
    - Anderson
    - Bailey
    - Esleck
    - Hays
    - Moran, [2 items]
    - Ray
    - Roberts
    - Rutherford
    - Unidentified [Graham?]
  - Football games, 1922-1923, n.d., [8 items]
  - Football team, 1923, n.d., [2 items]
  - Tennis team, 1923-1926, [2 items]
  - Track team members, 1923
    - Brittingham
    - Potts
    - Smith
  - Track meets, 1922-1924, [7 items]
  - Unidentified team [probably cross-country], n.d.
  - Barrack fire, 1924
  - Freshman pillow fight, ca. 1923
  - Barrack roof painted by rats, 1924
  - Snake dance at football game, 1922
  - Sophomore night, 1924, [2 items]
  - Unidentified group [possibly Monogram Club initiation], ca. 1925
  - Cadet parades and formations, 1922-1924, n.d., [11 items]
  - Rat parades, 1922, n.d., [9 items]
  - Campus scenes, n.d.
    - YMCA Building
    - Unidentified buildings, [4 items]
    - Snow-covered trees